{"tossups": [{"question": "This man is the subject of a biography by Robert Wilson subtitled \u201cAn American Life,\" and this man funded a series of renovation projects in Connecticut that were part of his \u201cprofitable philanthropy.\u201d This man once testified against William Mumler, who was considered a \u201cspirit photographer.\u201d This businessman once offered to provide $500 to anyone who could demonstrate the ability to speak with the dead and became known as the prince of the \u201chumbug\" hoax. Claiming \u201ca sucker is born every minute,\" for ten points, who was this businessman who founded a circus with James Anthony Bailey?", "answer": "Phineas Taylor <b><u>Barnum</u></b> (or P.T. <b><u>Barnum</u></b>; accept <b><u>Barnum</u></b> and Bailey)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This person expressed their appreciation for Cox\u2019s Orange Pippin apples and Wensleydale cheese in the essay <em>In Defence of English Cooking</em>. One book by this author notes that mining households spend only \"ten pence a week on green vegetables and ten pence half-penny on milk..., and nothing on fruit.\" That book by this author was written after studying the working class in Lancashire and Yorkshire. For ten points, name this English author of <em>The Road to Wigan Pier</em> who coined authoritarian psychology terms like \"thoughtcrime\" and \"doublethink\" in the novel <em>1984</em>.", "answer": "George <b><u>Orwell</u></b> (or Eric Arthur <b><u>Blair</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This body of water was described by Ant\u00f3nio Galv\u00e3o as a \u201cdragon\u2019s tail.\u201d Philip Parker King spent five years surveying the area surrounding this body of water, and for thousands of years, indigenous groups, such as the Kaw\u00e9sqar, inhabited this body of water. The Treaty of Peace and Friendship of 1984 between two bordering countries recognized this body of water as a demilitarized zone. For ten points, what \"Strait\" on the southern tip of South America is named for a Portuguese explorer?", "answer": "Strait(s) of <b><u>Magellan</u></b> (or Estrecho de <b><u>Magallanes</u></b>; accept Estrecho de <b><u>Todos los</u></b> <b><u>Santos</u></b> or Strait(s) of <b><u>All Saints</u></b> before \"explorer\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Carlos Salinas's tenure as president of this company included the arrest of the union boss Jos\u00e9 Hern\u00e1ndez Galicia, who was using violent force to coerce the syndicates of workers. Following the creation of this company, former Secretary of Agriculture Saturnino Cedillo [[seh-DEE-yoh]] declared the sitting government illegitimate and revolted from his power base. Citing Article 27 of the Constitution of 1917, L\u00e1zaro C\u00e1rdenas ordered the creation of this company after seizing Anglo-Dutch and American holdings. The national oil company of Mexico is, for ten points, what state enterprise created in the 1930s?", "answer": "<b><u>PEMEX</u></b> (accept <b><u>Petr\u00f3leos Mexicanos</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "As the head of Charles University, this man affirmed his nation's neutrality in the Western Schism. This man is credited with developing a dot above a diacritic which later became the h\u00e1\u010dek [[HAH-chek]] for a language he helped to codify in his <em>Orthographia</em> <em>bohemica</em>. While he believed in transubstantiation, this man was heavily influenced by John Wycliffe and was condemned as a heretic at the Council of Constance. For ten points, name this Bohemian theologian who was burned at the stake and names a series of wars with the Holy Roman Empire fought after his death.", "answer": "Jan <b><u>Hus</u></b> (or John <b><u>Huss</u></b>; or John <b><u>Hus</u></b>; accept <b><u>Hus</u></b>site; or <b><u>Hus</u></b>site Wars)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In a Supreme Court case, this treaty was deemed \u201cuseless\u201d by Chief Justice James Pendergast. The similar Batman\u2019s Treaty was signed in a nearby country five years before this treaty, in which over 500 representatives of one side were presented with a non-English version. In addition to working on its central country\u2019s Declaration of Independence, James Busby helped draft this treaty with William Hobson. Negotiated in 1840 in a country containing Mount Cook, for ten points, what was this treaty through which lands were ceded by the Maori?", "answer": "Treaty of <b><u>Waitangi</u></b> [[wye-TAHN-gee]] (or Te Tiriti o <b><u>Waitangi</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This campaign was announced with a tweet stating, \u201cWe must now realize the promise of America by trusting God, unifying our vision and building our future.\u201d Over 600 petition signatures from this campaign were claimed to be fraudulent due to \u201cnearly identical handwriting and others [lacking] complete addresses.\u201d Michelle Tidball, a preacher from Wyoming, was selected to be the running mate for this campaign's candidate. For ten points, what campaign for the Birthday Party was announced by a Chicago rapper to run for president of the United States?", "answer": "<b><u>Kanye</u></b> West <b><u>2020</u></b> presidential campaign (accept either <b><u>Kanye</u></b> or <b><u>West</u></b>; accept <b><u>Ye for President</u></b>; accept obvious equivalents)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man narrowly avoided the same fate as Elijah Lovejoy at a speech given by George Thompson. A faction led by Lewis Tappan split off from this man\u2019s organization over the election of Abby Kelley. This leader publicly burned a copy of the Constitution in protest, calling it \u201ca covenant of death.\u201d This man was a close ally of Wendell Phillips, who succeeded him as president of the American Anti-Slavery Society. For ten points, name this fierce abolitionist and orator who published <em>The Liberator</em>.", "answer": "William Lloyd <b><u>Garrison</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The last person to receive this award was Hayley Mills for her performance in the 1960 film <em>Pollyanna</em>. This award was established after Jackie Cooper\u2019s performance in the film <em>Skippy</em> lost to Lionel Barrymore. Bob Hope called this award the \u201cOscarette\u201d when presenting it to Margaret O\u2019Brien. First won by Shirley Temple in 1934, for ten points, what now-discontinued award recognized child actors and actresses for their performances in film?", "answer": "<b><u>Academy Juvenile</u></b> Award (accept <b><u>Juvenile Oscar</u></b>; accept <b><u>Juvenile Academy</u> </b>Award; accept <b><u>Oscarette</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "In reference to this politician, a billionaire once said, \u201cPlease don\u2019t call the manager on me.\u201d This politician claimed that a certain quality \u201chas been part of my story, I guess, since the day I was born.\" Elon Musk once compared this politician to his \u201cfriend\u2019s angry mom\u201d and referred to her as \u201cKaren\u201d while noting his high tax contributions. During his first presidential campaign, Donald Trump repeatedly called this woman \u201cPocahontas\u201d in reference to her claims of being part-Native American. For ten points, name this progressive Democratic Massachusetts senator.", "answer": "Elizabeth <b><u>Warren</u></b> (or Elizabeth Ann <b><u>Warren</u></b>; accept Elizabeth Ann <b><u>Herring</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "In the 1990s, an activist group made up of employees of this company known as Fuerza Unida [[FWEHR-zah oo-NEE-dah]] led a campaign against it for higher pay. A Latvian immigrant, named Jacob Davis, co-founded this company and came up with a patent to utilize copper rivets. Overalls began to be sold by this business in the 1870s, a few decades after its namesake founder originally operated a business on 90 Sacramento Street in a city where miners flocked during the California Gold Rush. Denim is heavily utilized by, for ten points, what company, the first to manufacture blue jeans?", "answer": "<b><u>Levi</u></b> Strauss & Co. (or <b><u>Levi</u></b>\u2019s)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Project FUBELT aimed to prevent this man from ascending to power. This man attained his highest office by obtaining a plurality vote over Jorge Alessandri as a candidate for the Popular Unity Coalition. This man appointed general Carlos Prats to the cabinet as his Minister of the Interior. This man gave his last speech while enemy troops were storming the La Moneda Palace and nationalized his country\u2019s copper mines. For ten points, identify this Marxist president of Chile who was succeeded by Augusto Pinochet.", "answer": "Salvador <b><u>Allende</u></b> [[ah-YEN-deh]] Gossens (or Salvador Guillermo <b><u>Allende</u> </b>Gossens)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "It's not Spain, but protests in this country erupted during the 1937 funerals of two supporters of Francisco Franco. The last living recipient of the Order of Victory was a leader of this country, who succeeded a non-Spanish Ferdinand I. During a 1941 massacre, this country was in control of Odessa. Michael I was a king of this country, another of whose leaders feuded with Horia Sima, the head of its Iron Guard. Once led by Ion Antonescu, for ten points, what is this European country governed from Bucharest?", "answer": "<b><u>Romania</u></b> (accept Kingdom of <b><u>Romania</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Following a defeat to this city state, Argia searched for the dead body of her husband then unsuccessfully tried to revive him with tears and kisses. The Nemean Games were founded while a group was en route to this city. Adrastus was the leader of the aforementioned group which aimed to restore a brother of Ismene and Antigone [[an-TIG-oh-nee]] to the throne of this city. The \u201cSeven Against [this city]\" assisted one side in a conflict between the sons of an exiled king who married his mother. For ten points, name this Greek city-state legendarily ruled by Oedipus.", "answer": "<b><u>Thebes</u></b> (or <b><u>Th\u00edva</u></b>; or <b><u>Th\u00eabai</u></b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "Two members of this family were accompanied by the ambassador Koeketei on a trip in which a <em>paiza</em> was to be bestowed upon the pope. An outpost at Sandak on the Crimean Peninsula was established by the aforementioned brothers from this family whose nephew wrote about Manji in a work sometimes referred to as <em>Il Milione</em> [[ill-mill-YOH-neh]]. That member of this family lived during the 13th century and served in Kublai Khan\u2019s court. For ten points, identify this family that included the Venetian traveler Marco.", "answer": "<b><u>Polo</u></b> family (accept Marco <b><u>Polo</u></b>; acceptNiccolo <b><u>Polo</u></b>; accept Maffeo <b><u>Polo</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "During the War of 1812, Fort Howard was constructed on this body of water. A self-proclaimed Mormon king, named James Strang, reigned for six years on a major island within this body of water. The first European to visit this body of water was Jean Nicolet. Voyageurs led by the explorers Marquette and Jolliet followed this lake until reaching the Fox River near Green Bay. For ten points, name this Great Lake which saw a massive uptick in shipping with the growth of Chicago.", "answer": "Lake <b><u>Michigan</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "Manasseh Cutler helped secure Congressional support for this bill, after which a group called \u201cthe forty-eight\u201d established a settlement at Marietta. Nathan Dane claimed to have authored the sixth article of this act which included a prohibition on slavery. A five-man government was to run this act\u2019s central location while its population was under five thousand. A provision on natural rights in this act is thought to have influenced the Bill of Rights written two years later. For ten points, name this act which created a territory encompassing an area now including Indiana and Ohio.", "answer": "<b><u>Northwest Ordinance</u></b> of 1787 (accept An <b><u>Ordinance for the Government of</u></b> <b><u>the Territory of the United States, [a]North-West</u></b> of the River Ohio; accept <b><u>Ordinance of</u></b> <b><u>1787</u></b>; do not accept or prompt on <b><u>Northwest Ordinance of 1789</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "William Shockley is often called the \"father of [this region]\" a result of his attempts to commercialize his transistor design. Frederick Terman is often credited with personally nurturing several firms that developed in this region, like Lockheed Martin and Hewlett-Packard. Made a popular site due to its proximity to Stanford University, for ten points, what is this region in Northern California known for headquartering many pioneering technology corporations?", "answer": "<b><u>Silicon Valley</u></b> (prompt on \"San Jose\" or \"Palo Alto\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>A leader of a rebel group in this country, Datu Amil, was killed at the Battle of</u></b> <b><u>Bud Bagsak, one of the final battles of a rebellion in which rebels were massacred at</u></b> <b><u>Bud Dajo. The Organic Act and Jones (+)</u> Act attempted to formalize a parliament in this occupied country. A president of this country was captured the Battle of Tirad Pass. This country's Moro population was suppressed with assistance from John Pershing. Manuel (*)</b> Quezon became the first president of, for ten points, what country that gained independence in the Treaty of Manila?", "answer": "<b><u>Philippine</u></b>s (accept Republika ng <b><u>Pilipinas</u></b>; accept First <b><u>Philippine</u></b> Republic)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>After heading the EPA, Lisa Jackson was hired by this man to improve his</u></b> <b><u>company\u2019s environmental footprint. Chief Design Officer Jony Ive has reported to this</u></b> <b><u>man, who ascended to the CEO position after his predecessor became chairman six</u></b> <b><u>weeks before (+)</u> dying of pancreatic cancer in 2011. Following an attack that killed fourteen people in San Bernardino, this man\u2019s company was asked to create custom firmware to get around the security protocols of the (*) </b>iPhone. For ten points, name this CEO of Apple since 2011.", "answer": "Tim <b><u>Cook</u></b> (accept Timothy Donald <b><u>Cook</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>The so-called \"Green Count\" of Savoy and the late arrival of his five hundred</u></b> <b><u>men to this battle may have led to his ally's decisive defeat. The sacred banner known</u></b> <b><u>as the</u> </b><em><b><u>oriflamme</u></b></em><b><u> was abandoned by its bearer at this battle, and the siege of Calais</u></b> <b><u>[[cah-LAY]] (+)</u> occurred in the immediate aftermath of this battle. A muddy environment slowed the charge of knights under Phillip VI at this battle, resulting in the English foot infantry and longbowmen quickly routing them. Edward the (*) </b>Black Prince orchestrated, for ten points, which early victory by the English during the Hundred Years' War?", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Cr\u00e9cy</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This building was built on land purchased by the mining magnates Mott and</u></b> <b><u>Samuel Newhouse. The term \u201c23 skidoo\u201d is thought to have arisen near this building</u></b> <b><u>which originally did not include women\u2019s restrooms. Originally built to serve as an</u></b> <b><u>office for the George A. Fuller (+)</u> Company, this Burnham-designed building now lends its name to a district of Manhattan. Found on Fifth Avenue, this building was intended to fill in a (*) </b>wedge-shaped gap at the intersection with Broadway. For ten points, name this New York skyscraper with a distinctive triangular shape.", "answer": "<b><u>Flatiron</u></b> Building (accept <b><u>Fuller</u></b> Building before mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 2004, the Badeschiff [[BAH-deh-shiff]] floating swimming pool was opened</u></b> <b><u>on this body of water. At Eisenh\u00fcttenstadt [[\"EYE\"-zen-HOO-ten-shtaht]], formerly</u></b> <b><u>known as Stalinstadt, this river's Dahme [[DAH-meh]] tributary is linked to the Oder</u></b> <b><u>via a canal. One building along this river housed the Volkskammer (+)</u> and was torn down in 2006. That building was the Palace of the Republic which was on this river's Museum Island (*) </b>along with the Bode [[BOH-deh]] Museum. For ten points, name this tributary of the Havel river that runs through Berlin.", "answer": "<b><u>Spree</u></b> River [[SHPRAY]] (or <b><u>Sprjewja</u></b>; or <b><u>Spr\u00e9va</u></b>; be lenient on pronunciation)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>A king of these people was forced to sign an \"Edict of Toleration\" following the</u></b> <b><u>arrival of Cyrille Laplace's warship,</u> </b><em><b><u>Artemise</u></b></em><b><u> [[ahr-teh-MEESE]]. These people kept a</u></b> <b><u>specific breed of canine which was fed Taro root and meant to be (+)</u> consumed rather than kept as a pet. The nobility of these Marquesan Island-descended people kept same-sex lovers known as </b><em><b>aikane</b></em><b>, with one chief even asking James Cook to allow him to take Cook's astronomer as a partner. The (*) </b>Kamehameha family was the royal dynasty of, for ten points, which Polynesian people?", "answer": "<b><u>Hawai'i</u></b>ans (accept <b><u>Marquesan</u></b>s before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In a novel predominantly set in this state, Marie Lazarre marries her rapist,</u></b> <b><u>Nector, while June Morrissey freezes to death en route to a reservation. A novel set in</u></b> <b><u>this state that frequently references the U.S.'s entry into World War One centers on a</u></b> <b><u>woman who fails to work with the Jolly Seventeen (+)</u> and the Thanatopsis Club. The novel </b><em><b>Love Medicine</b></em><b> draws from Louise Erdrich's experiences in a Chippewa community in this state. Gopher Prarie resident Carol (*) </b>Kennicott lives in, for ten points, what state, the setting of Sinclair Lewis's <em>Main Street</em>?", "answer": "<b><u>Minnesota</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Kingdom of Da\u02bfamat was a likely indigenous state in this modern-day</u></b> <b><u>country that controlled cities including Matara and Qohaito. The Gash Group</u></b> <b><u>flourished in the neolithic period in this country, where excavations have been</u></b> <b><u>conducted at Sembel. The Medri (+)</u> Bahri kingdom ruled this country before its conquest by a southern neighbor, after which it fell under the control of General Oreste [[or-REST-eh]] Baratieri of the Italian Empire. (*) </b>Set free by the UNOVER referendum, for ten points, what is this Red Sea-bordering nation that gained independence from Ethiopia in 1993?", "answer": "State of <b><u>Eritrea</u></b> (or Hagere <b><u>Ertra</u></b>; Editor's Note: \"Da'amat\" or \"D'mt\" is not to be confused with the much later Kingdom of \"Damot\" of western Ethiopia.", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>While Governor of Ujjain, this man married a merchant's daughter named</u></b> <b><u>Devi whose lack of royal blood led to her exclusion from the title of</u> </b><em><b><u>agramahisi</u></b></em><b><u>, or</u></b> <b><u>Chief Queen. This ruler maintained a namesake \"hell\" (+)</u> prison wherein he supposedly had Chandagirika torture people, including possibly having his own brother executed for being a Jain. A Greek ambassador named Dionysius visited the court of Bindusara and this man, who supposedly was overwhelmed by (*) </b>violence he had unleashed in Kalinga. For ten points, name this Buddhist-convert Emperor of the Mauryan dynasty of India.", "answer": "<b><u>Ashoka</u></b> the Great (accept <b><u>Asoka</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}